Within the first month, we did $50,000 in business
without any advertising.
And within 11 months, we were doing almost as much
as the security company.
And within four years, we're doing 120 million in sales.
What's going on, everyone?
Welcome back to episode seven
of 10 Questions with a Millionaire.
I'm James with the School of Hard Knocks,
and I'm here with Glen Boyd.
He's a founder of a major tech company.
We're super excited to be with you today.
Just kind of ask you some questions about your journey.
Could you kind of give us a little rundown
about your story?
I started my career really young,
teaching myself to program.
Then in my early 20s, started a tech company
that ended up taking public in 99.
It was one of the early dot-com companies.
As they say, I got out before it all crashed
and it did really well, but I took it public
and then ended up selling
it in a merger later on.
Your first company was originally called EG Software,
I believe?
That's correct.
At that time, how did you
know that that was the idea,
that you were gonna take it to market?
And how did you know that that was the company
that you wanted to kind of
invest in and go all in with?
The original product was not that.
The original product was actually a security product.
And what it does is
it was like a surveillance system
for internal networks,
because the internet really hadn't been invented yet
or it wasn't being utilized.
But there was a lot of local area networks.
Most of the banks and financial institutions
were being pushed to put
in some type of audit control
as more and more things were becoming computerized.
I saw an opportunity and wrote a product
for logging and analyzing all the traffic
and all the access of what goes on
on a local area network.
We had a great, amazing little business.
We had the entire Federal Reserve.
We had almost every major bank in the US.
It was me, my partner, Ellie,
and my wife worked in the business.
And my brother-in-law, there was four of us,
and we were banging out a million dollars a year
out of a little office
about the size of this room.
All of a sudden, the internet comes along.
Yahoo had gone public, Netscape,
and I realized the world's gonna change.
Here it is, I had
been working in local area networks,
but now all of a sudden,
the whole world is becoming networked.
And we looked at, like, well,
how do we capitalize on that?
And I think the analogy I
gave at the time to Ellie
is I said, look, you know,
I see this train going past,
and I see people on that train,
and they're all got champagne glasses.
I said, if we start running now,
we might be able to catch
the last car of that train,
because this is going to be the future.
So we spent the whole summer trying to figure out
what product we were gonna go into
and what we were going to do,
almost willing to abandon our really successful business.
Then, I don't know if it was him or me,
but we had this epiphany that is that we pivoted
from the company.
So instead of having this product
that analyzed local traffic and looking for,
say, security violations in a bank, potential fraud,
it started analyzing anonymous traffic
that was coming into the web,
and instead of producing, say, a security report,
it produced a marketing report.
So instead of trying to find somebody
who was committing fraud, we said,
what if you analyze all this anonymous data
and identified how many people are interested in this,
and how many people are interested in that?
So some of our earliest clients and customers
were people like Sports Illustrated Magazine.
They had a website, everybody was brand new,
but they didn't know if they had 100,000 people coming
or 10,000 people coming and visiting it 10 times
because there was no product to
be able to tell them that.
But I had this technology
that we had spent years building
that could analyze massive amounts of data very quickly,
and we pivoted.
We had no idea if
the product was gonna be successful.
We didn't know if the
dogs would eat the dog food.
Within the first month, we did $50,000 in business
without any advertising, and within 11 months,
we were doing almost as much
as the security company.
And within four years, we
were doing 120 million in sales.
A lot of people, they
tend to have these great ideas,
but they really struggle to get the funding for them.
So what do you recommend to people
that are trying to get that funding
for their ideas to build companies?
Well, it always helps to have something demonstrable
and not just an idea.
Ideas are really difficult to get funded,
and if you can build something that's a sample,
something that you can demonstrate,
I mean, that goes a long, long way.
There's an old expression that I think was founded
in the 70s, and it happened to do
with all these advertising companies.
These advertising companies were creating,
I think it was called the dog food wars,
where they're creating all these different dog foods,
and they spent all this money,
and they put them on television,
but it turns out the dogs
just didn't like the dog food,
and it didn't matter how great the advertising was
or how flashy it was.
So the expression, especially in the tech world,
was will the dogs eat the dog food?
And what that meant is
will people actually use the product?
So often, you don't know completely
until you build a product or build some of it,
and if you can get early adoption,
even if it's a small amount,
you can typically demonstrate a path
to where somebody will be willing to invest in it,
because they can say, wow,
this is really not only a good idea,
but I can see how people are using it,
and they're really gravitating towards it,
and there's a huge chance of it exploding.
I mean, you just look at some of the examples,
whether it was YouTube that started out
with just cat videos, or Instagram that just started out
with people wanting to share some of their personal photos
to almost every tech company.
They started as some little simple idea,
but it really went viral,
and it's a huge success.
It really went to the level
of the dogs love the dog food.
In today's world, we're seeing a lot of light
being shined on self-improvement, personal development.
For you throughout your career,
what would you say was
some of the most pivotal things
that you incorporated, whether it was into your routine
or just throughout your life
that led you to where you are today?
For any entrepreneur, it's always a challenge,
and it definitely was for me, keeping life-work balance.
Even more so as I'm older, it's life-health-work balance.
Started very young, had children very young,
and I had a high-tech, super-high-tech dog,
super-successful company very young.
Through that process, I ended up divorced early on.
Some of that was with
the stress of starting a company
and having young children and having a young marriage.
That was where I think some of that life-work balance
broke down.
Later on in life, I
ended up having a heart attack
and a triple bypass surgery.
Some of that led to me
to realize that I have to,
as I'm getting older, take my health almost as seriously
as my physical health is
as seriously as my mental health,
as well as conquering the boredom of life.
It's easy to find yourself
working too much as an entrepreneur because you love it,
but not everybody else around you can appreciate that,
and that's where your relationships can suffer,
whether it's with your significant other
or with your family.
How can someone prioritize their mental health?
What were some of the
steps that you learned to take
during that process to focus on
your personal and mental health?
Anybody who's looking for a good
entrepreneurial work-life balance,
I would encourage them to partner with somebody.
I think there's no way I
could have ever built my company
if I hadn't have a strong co-partner,
and I think that's what
I learned in founding the company,
and we were able to offload
a lot of things for each other,
whether it was somebody has a personal emergency
or just dividing up the work,
and finding somebody you trust is critical,
and somebody you enjoy working with,
and also somebody who has not just complimentary,
but even non-complementary skills
so that you both bring something to the table
that the other one doesn't have.
What was the biggest risk that you ever took,
and how important has risk been to you?
I had a newborn on the way,
and gotten down to probably the last,
I think, $1,000 in my bank account.
Oh, actually, I had some money saved up.
I quit my job and started writing my first product,
and got down to the
last $1,000 into my bank account
and went and sold the one
asset I had at the time,
which is a motorcycle.
That got us through another month or two.
Then my business partner, he came on board
and put his personal money in,
and the two of us together went on
to make a very successful company,
but to say that I
put it all on the line
is not an understatement.
At the time, I had a lot of
money, and I had a lot of money,
and I had a lot of money,
and I had a lot of money.
My total risk mentality was the worst thing
that can happen to me is
I'll have to go get a job.
For me, it was like,
let me take all this risk,
even though I had a newborn on the way.
I knew that if I failed, I'll
just have to go get a job,
but I also knew that if I didn't try it,
I would be sitting at a job someplace
always wondering, why didn't I try?
When you're creating a company,
it's important to build a strong leadership team.
What are the three most important traits
that you look for in people when you're assembling,
like a company?
a leadership team or employing people for a
company? Well, I think you have to work with
honest people. You have to work with intelligent
people. You have to work with people that they
can take constructive feedback, and that includes
yourself. I think that's critical. You're not
always going to get along. Our wives at the time,
in our first early days of the founding of the
company, they thought that my partner and I were
going to kill each other because we were constantly
arguing. But what we were doing is really fleshing
out the best path forward or the best idea
forward. I remember in the early days, we
had some horatious arguments over which shade of red
we were going to make our first packaging on
our product. And it turned out to be this inconsequential
kind of thing. But eventually, through that
process, we became closer and closer friends
and trusted each other more and more to
make independent decisions. And we needed to go
through that early on to order get to that
level of confidence with each other. What would you say
is the worst financial decision that you've
made throughout your life? Getting involved in things
you don't want to be involved
in. I had this misfortune of doing,
a construction loan on a business that I really didn't
want to be in. I got kind of talked into
it with another friend of mine. It was
supposed to be a temporary construction loan. Everything
was collateralized. The management was failing. I had to
step in and spend a couple of years of
my life turning it around only to have the
whole thing because of a tragic accident. And somebody,
unfortunately, passed away. It ended up costing the
entire company. I lost close to $3 million
on that. And what that taught me is don't
get involved in something you don't want to get
involved in.
My gut instinct was telling me from day one,
don't do it. But I ended up doing it anyway.
Then I powered through and thought. And by
circumstance, I wished I'd just never done it.
But what was the best
financial decision that you've ever made?
Probably for us, both my partner and I
at the time when we founded the company,
the best decision was the company
was growing so fast. We were profitable,
but we felt like we needed additional capital
just to expand faster. And we sought out a
venture capital firm. And we spent a lot of energy
working with them because venture capital came out of the blue.
You can spend and take a lot
of attention. It's like there's a courtship
that goes on. And in the end, they decided
to pass on us. We were kind of glad because
we were so frustrated with them and the process,
so they ended up not investing in us. What that
meant though is we didn't have that
financial underpinning that you would with venture capital,
but we also were way more frugal with
the decisions we made going forward. And when
we took the company public, he
and I own 95% of the company.
What is your best piece of advice to
someone trying to scale?
their business? Keep your expenses controlled. The
problem with scaling is that expenses scale
as well. The numbers become multiple. So, you
know, one bad dip someplace can wipe out your
whole business, especially if you're trying to
stay profitable, especially if you're trying to
grow really fast, you know, just keep
your expenses under control. What are the three
books that you'd recommend that any entrepreneur
should read? My favorite that changed my, it
probably saved my business or helped me understand
my business. There's actually two of them, but one
more than anything else. At the time, my business
was growing so fast, but I couldn't quite put my
finger on what the problems were. I would
come home because I'd had these hellaciously stressful
days and I would try to read some just so
I could sleep. And I started reading into thin air and
then it clicked for me what the problem was
with my company. In the book, he talks about everybody
has a level where they run out of oxygen when
they go up in altitude. And even the simplest task,
when you get up to a certain level,
like tying your shoes becomes very, very difficult.
And everybody's built differently. And unless you
have supplemental oxygen, some people will tap out
and it becomes deadly. And the only solution is
to go down the mountain. There are some people that
are natural athletes who can, you know, they're
Sherpas because they were born with the genetics,
their blood to carry the oxygen can go all
the way to the top of Mount Everest without
supplemental oxygen. Extremely rare, but it does happen.
But what I was finding is because my
company was growing so fast, somebody that was an employee
six months ago or a year ago who I hired
and was just an amazing employee was failing. And it
dawned on me that I was going to have to
have to go down the mountain. And so I was like,
I'm going to have to go down the mountain. And I
started out and they were working, maybe managing
four people or six people or 10 people because
that's what I hired them at that level to do.
And then a year later or six months later, they're
managing 20 people or 30 people. And it's the same
analogy as if you're good at juggling and you can
juggle three balls and I hand you a fourth and
you're good at that and you hand you a fifth,
a sixth, eventually you're going to reach the
level where you're going to drop all the balls.
And what I realized is it was my responsibility
to stop handing them balls and also in some cases,
take them down the mountain.
My hiring practices so that when I would hire
somebody, I would say, okay, so I know we were
hiring you for to manage 20 people and you managed
50 in the past, but you'll be managing 50 people
within a year. And I need somebody who can, who's
already been up the mountain. So that book to me
saved my company, you know, and once we
identified that we changed our hiring practices across the
company to hire above the level for the position
that we were doing and people that were used to
be good, that were starting to fail. We
took them down the mountain and divided up their
responsibilities. Another one, which
is, it's great for marketing.
And if we're launching a new product is
called crossing the chasm. And it's talking about the
process and there's this chasm in the bell curve
of getting your product across before it gets into
adoption. And it really resonated in the early days
when we were trying to grow our product and
how to launch it into new markets. You sold
your company for over a billion dollars. So my question
for you is, you know, you, you made a
lot of money off that. Does money buy happiness? No.
Why? It just doesn't. I think there's
a certain level that money does. I mean,
I grew up very poor. I roof houses as a child
in the Texas heat to help my dad and then later
washing dishes with my mother. Yes. Money
definitely bought happiness when you reach a
certain level beyond that. When I finally was able
to feel secure enough that I could send my
children to college. And that gave me a lot more
freedom to try new things. But at a certain level,
the champagne doesn't get any better. And
a certain level, the women don't get prettier
or a certain level, the beaches don't get
any nicer. Just making more and more money doesn't
buy happiness, but there is.
Probably a base level somewhere between
poverty and paying all your bills.
If you were to go back to, you know, when
you're 18 years old and you could have a conversation
with a younger Glenn, what are the three pieces
of advice that you would tell yourself in a
conversation with your younger self? I
mean, I definitely would have said,
enjoy life a little bit more. I mean, I,
I didn't really have a childhood, but that was also
because I started working so young and
was successful young, but I also, the intensity
of it, I had to process that later in my
life after I sold my company. It was like actually
learning how to do it. And I think that's a
really good point. I think that's a really good point.
It's about learning how to enjoy life, you know, not
just work, work, work, work. And so I think I would
tell my 18 year old self is like, maybe not
be so ambitious and finish college, maybe not be so
ambitious and have a little bit deeper, meaningful
relationships here or there. Other advice I'd give
myself, I think I would tell myself to take
care of my health better because I think that's the
first and easiest thing to let go. As an
entrepreneur, when you're working, you just can't get away from
working 50, 60, 70 hours a week.
Yeah.
If you're not physically doing it, you're thinking
about it when you're at home, you're here, you're
there. That translates into your relationships. Don't
spend so much money once you finally make
it. Better yet would be get some really
good financial advice once you finally do make good
money.
We've interviewed hundreds of millionaires and one of
the biggest pieces of advice that they would
tell their younger selves is they wish that
they would have started sooner. For someone who has
all these thoughts and great ideas and they're
always saying, oh, I'll start tomorrow, I'll start
tomorrow, whether it's a YouTube channel or the
internet, I'm going to start tomorrow. I'm going
to start tomorrow and I'm going to start tomorrow,
I'm going to start tomorrow. It's a really good
way to start that journey.
You've created a channel or this company, but
you actually executed, you created a company, you sold
it for a lot of money. What is your
advice to someone trying to really start and begin their
business?
Procrastination is your worst enemy, and I think
that's what you're getting at. It's easy to always
put it off and not do it and not take the
risk. The one thing we do not have in life that's
renewable is time. The longer you delay it, the longer
it's going to take you to get to where you
want to be. I think there's an
old expression. I think it's even a fact.
of if you're going to fail fail fast get in there
try it it didn't work move on do the next thing
because if you're an entrepreneur you're probably going
to be an entrepreneur your whole life and if
you're going to make a mistake and have a failure get
it out of the way and go learn from that and
do the next one and the longer you delay
for that perfect idea that just means you're that much
further away from a success well guys that wraps
up today's episode of 10 questions with a millionaire
we were super excited to be able to sit down
here with glenn glenn thank you so much for coming on
and it was great to meet you talk to you
find out more about your story today so stay tuned
guys for more content if you enjoyed this
video make sure that you like leave us a
subscribe we got a ton of
great content coming let's get it